Imagine giving a a super smart AI a million pages of your company's standard operating procedures. You'd think it would become your absolute best
employee, right? Like capable of doing anything.
>> the dream. You just feed it everything and assume it's going to work perfectly.
>> Right, but the science shows it actually gets dumber. You hand it this massive encyclopedia and it acts like someone who just, you know, threw a giant
instruction manual into a blender.
>> It's a really fundamental misunderstanding of how these models actually process information.
I mean, we we assume more context equals more capability, but in reality it just creates this massive attention dilution.
>> And that is exactly what we are tearing apart today. Welcome to the deep dive.
Today we're looking at the day three white paper from the five day of AI agents vibe coding intensive course by Google X Kaggle.
>> It's a really fascinating read.
>> It is. And you know, if you're a technical Kaggle competitor looking to squeeze every drop of performance out of your agent architecture, or even if
you're just intensely curious about how AI actually executes complex tasks behind the scenes, this deep dive is absolutely for you.
>> Yeah, there's a lot to unpack here.
>> We are uncovering why dumping data into massive AI context windows is, frankly, a recipe for disaster. And why this simple lightweight primitive called an
agent skill is quietly replacing the entire bloated multi-agent ecosystem.
>> It's a massive paradigm shift. I mean, we spent the last few years building these incredibly complex networks of like manager agents and worker agents.
>> whole swarm thing.
>> Exactly, trying to brute force specialized behavior. But agent skills completely sidestep that complexity.
They turn a single general purpose AI into a hyper specialist, but um only for the exact seconds you need it to be.
>> Let's start with the physical anatomy of this, because when I first read the term agent skill, I pictured some uh really dense compiled binary code or a deep
neural network weight adjustment.
>> Oh yeah, like some complicated fine-tuning process.
>> but it's actually shockingly simple at a structural level.
>> It really is. At its core, an agent skill is literally just a folder on your file system.
>> Wait, just a folder?
>> Just a folder.
Inside that folder, you have one mandatory markdown file called skill.md.
And you can think of this as the brain of the skill.
>> Okay.
>> It contains the metadata. So, the name and a very precise description of when to use it, along with the core instructions.
>> Yeah.
>> And then, around that file, you have optional subdirectories that handle all the heavy lifting.
>> Right, I noticed the paper breaks down those subdirectories into three specific types. There's a scripts folder, a references folder, and an assets folder.
>> Yeah.
>> Why do we need all of those if the skill.md already has the instructions?
>> Because you really want to separate the what to do from the how to do it deterministically.
>> Oh, I see.
>> The scripts folder holds actual executable code, like, you know, Python or bash scripts. If the agent needs to calculate a cryptographic hash, you
don't want the language model guessing the math.
>> Definitely not. You want it to just run a script.
>> Exactly. Python script that does it perfectly every time. Then, the references folder is for dense domain context, like a 50-page PDF of tax
codes, which is way too long for the main prompt. And the assets folder holds things like JSON schemas or email templates.
The whole folder structure isolates the moving parts.
>> And the paper outlines two distinct paths for how these skills actually get written in the real world.
Path A is driven by subject matter experts. So, I'm picturing um an HR manager who has an onboarding guide, or maybe a compliance officer
with a massive run book.
>> Right.
>> They don't need to learn Python. They just translate their existing human instructions into this skill.md format.
>> Precisely. It really democratizes agent creation. You don't have to be a software engineer to build a skill.
>> But path B is different, right?
>> Yeah, path B comes from the developer side and it's much more dynamic. A developer might watch an agent successfully stumble through a really
complex multi-step workflow.
>> Okay.
>> And they take that successful trace, clean up and crystallize it into a reusable skill folder. Next time the agent doesn't have to burn compute
figuring it all out from scratch.
>> It sounds a lot like a restaurant kitchen.
>> A restaurant kitchen, how so?
>> Well, the skill.md metadata is essentially the menu out front. The agent, our chef, reads the menu to know what's available.
>> Okay, I like that.
>> chef doesn't actually plug in the blender, which would be our scripts folder, or read the exact grandma's recipe out of the references folder
until a customer actually walks in and orders that specific dish.
>> That is a highly accurate way to visualize it.
The technical term the white paper uses for this is progressive disclosure.
>> Progressive disclosure?
>> Yeah. You only reveal the complex mechanics of a task when the task is actively triggered.
>> But wait, a lot of developers listening to this are probably screaming at their dashboards right now because they already use MCP, the model context
protocol.
>> Oh, sure.
>> Or they just keep a giant agents.md file in their project root. Aren't those tools already doing this exact thing?
>> It's a common confusion, actually, but the distinction is absolutely critical for system design.
MCP gives an agent reach.
>> Reach?
>> Right. An MCP server acts as a bridge connecting your agent to an external system like pulling a record from Salesforce or, you know, querying a big
query database.
>> Okay, so it connects to the outside world.
>> Exactly. A skill, on the other hand, gives the agent know-how. It's procedural memory. It's the step-by-step logic of what to do with that Salesforce
record once you actually have it.
>> So, the skill might say, "Here are the five steps to process a customer refund." And step two might be, "Use the MCP tool to check the database."
>> Exactly that. They compose beautifully together.
>> Mhm.
>> And regarding the agent.md file, that is global, always on context.
>> Like project-wide rules?
>> Yeah, like telling the AI, always write your code in TypeScript. Skills are strictly on demand.
>> That distinction brings us right into the token economics of this whole movement. Because if a skill is just a smartly organized folder, why did this
specific architecture explode in popularity, especially with the vibe coding crowd? You hinted earlier at the issue with dumping a million pages into a model.
>> Yeah, it solves a massive kind of hidden crisis in AI engineering known as context drought.
>> Context drought, sounds gross.
>> It is, computationally speaking. For a long time, the industry's naive assumption was that larger context windows would just magically solve all
our orchestration problems.
>> Just throw more context at it.
>> Right. If you have a 1 million token window, just dump every tool, every instruction, every API spec into the system prompt, and let the model figure it out.
>> But the paper references that famous lost in the middle study, and also a new 2025 study from Chroma research, they proved that across 18 different
frontier models, performance degrades silently as the input grows.
>> Silently is the keyword there. You don't get an error message, it just gets dumber.
>> Wow. So, even if the window can physically hold a million tokens, the model's accuracy, its ability to actually retrieve and use that
information, drops off a cliff long before the window fills up.
>> Because the attention mechanism literally gets diluted. Every extra token you add competes for the model's focus.
>> Yeah.
>> If your system prompt is cluttered with your instructions for 50 different tools, and the user just says hello,
>> Right.
>> the model is wasting compute ignoring 49 irrelevant tools.
>> So, progressive disclosure fixes this by keeping the noise out. If I have 50 workflows, I don't load them all, I just load the metadata, the trigger
descriptions.
>> Yes.
>> And the paper notes that might only be about 4,000 tokens.
When the user asks for a specific workflow, that single skill triggers and adds maybe 2,000 tokens for its active body.
The other 49 stay completely hidden on the hard drive.
>> You're taking 15,000 tokens of active heavy context and compressing it down to maybe 6,000.
The white paper shows this achieves up to a 98% reduction in active context.
>> 98%?
>> Yeah, it's huge. The model stays incredibly sharp because it's only looking at what actually matters in that moment.
>> Hold on, let me just I'm doing the math here. You said the metadata for 50 skills is 4,000 tokens.
>> Roughly, yeah.
>> If I'm an enterprise with 40,000 skills in my library, just reading the menu of metadata is going to blow out the context window anyway. How does
progressive disclosure survive at a massive corporate scale?
>> That's a great catch. At that scale, you don't even load all the metadata into the prompt.
>> Oh, you don't?
>> No, you use a lightweight retrieval system, a a rag pipeline.
>> Okay.
>> So, when the user types a prompt, a really fast embeddings model quickly scans the 40,000 skill descriptions, grabs the top five most relevant ones,
and only passes those five to the agent's context window.
>> Oh, wow.
>> It's progressive disclosure taken to the next level.
>> That completely reframes how I think about routing.
But, let me ask you this.
If we can just dynamically swap skills in and out of single agent, does that mean the traditional multi-agent architecture is dead?
Do we not need a manager agent routing tasks to a swarm of specialist worker agents anymore?
>> Multi-agent systems aren't dead, but their role is getting much, much narrower.
>> Okay, when do you still use them?
>> You still need them for genuine asynchronous parallelism.
Like having three agents research three different companies simultaneously.
Or when you have differing security postures.
>> Security posture?
>> Yeah. So, if you have an HR agent that needs clearance to read salaries, and a marketing agent scraping public websites, you keep those as separate
agents, so the marketing bot can't accidentally leak payroll data.
>> That makes perfect sense from a security standpoint.
>> almost everything else,
>> Mhm. the swarm approach is dying.
Let's say you're a logistics company with a hundred different process variants for shipping freight.
>> Right.
>> Maintaining a hundred different sub-agents with a hundred deployments, memory stores, and complex routing layers is just an operational nightmare. One
general purpose agent dynamically loading a hundred different skills from a folder is vastly more elegant.
>> Which sounds amazing until you realize the danger zone we're entering. I mean, if anyone in the company can write a skill just by typing up a markdown file,
it sounds like a recipe for absolute chaos.
>> absolutely can be.
>> If you're listening to this and you've ever watched your agent just completely ignore the custom tool you spent three hours writing, this next part is going
to hit close to home.
>> The reality is quite stark. The white paper references a 2025 study from Skills Bench that looked at real-world agent deployments. They found that 19%
of poorly designed skills actually caused the agent to perform worse than having no skill at all.
>> Wait, worse?
>> It actively subtracted baseline capability from the foundation model.
>> That's wild. And a Versel study found similar results, right? A 56% non-invocation rate, meaning more than half the time the agent just ignored the
skill completely. So, how exactly are these skills failing so catastrophically?
>> Well, the paper outlines four specific failure modes. First is trigger failure.
Your description's too vague, so the wrong skill fires, or the right one just stays quiet.
>> Okay.
>> Second is execution failure. It triggers correctly, but the internal instructions are messy, so it produces wild tool calls or hallucinates data.
>> Right.
>> Third is token budget failure. This is when the skill author dumps a massive unoptimized PDS into the references folder, blowing up the context window,
and ruining the agent's short-term memory.
>> And the fourth one is regression, which honestly feels like the most insidious.
You add a brand new skill to the library, and because its trigger phrase is too similar to an existing skill, it hijacks the routing.
>> Yes. You break a system that used to work perfectly just by adding something new.
>> Exactly.
>> This is why the white paper heavily mandates evaluation-driven development or EDD.
>> Right, EDD.
>> Before you write a single line of your skill.md file, you must write three JSON evaluation cases.
>> I love this concept. You have to define the input, the expected tools to be called, and the expected output format completely up front. If you don't know
what success looks like, you really have no business writing the instructions.
>> Yeah, exactly. You are testing the skill in isolation using a single skill sub-agent pattern.
>> Okay.
>> You give a blank agent only this one skill and run the JSON evals. But here's the critical part.
How you score those evaluations matters immensely. The paper dives deep into trajectory scoring.
>> I want to stop and unpack trajectory scoring because the paper mentions modes like exact, in order, or in order.
But like, if the user asks for a result and the agent delivers the correct final output, does it really matter how it got there?
>> It matters more than the final output itself.
>> Really?
>> A 2026 analysis by Latitude found that if you only score the final output, you'll pass 20 to 50% more test cases than if you score the trajectory,
meaning the specific sequence of tool calls.
>> Wait, if it's passing more cases, isn't that a good thing? We want it to pass.
>> Not if it's stumbling into the right answer through disastrous methods.
>> Uh.
>> Let's make this concrete. Imagine a user asks your customer service agent to refund my last order.
>> Okay.
>> The agent gets confused, pulls up the user's profile, accidentally deletes their shipping address, but then somehow successfully triggers the Stripe refund
API.
>> Oh, wow. That's terrible.
>> Right. If you were using output-only scoring, the test passes. The user got their money. But the trajectory was a complete disaster.
>> I see.
>> Trajectory scoring looks at the exact sequence of actions.
For a read-only skill, like summarizing a public document, maybe any order is fine. But for an action-allowed skill that touches production databases, you
absolutely need exact or in-order trajectory scoring to catch that deleted address.
>> So, if the model is just the engine block, I wouldn't let a brand new unproven engine drive my kids to school without testing the brakes in a
controlled environment first. There has to be a staging area, right? Like a sandbox where these skills run without actually pressing the buy button in the
real world.
>> You're anticipating the demo-to-deploy gap.
>> Right.
>> Confidence always peaks during the local demo, but it completely shatters in production. Teams immediately blame the model for hallucinating, but it's rarely
a model problem. It's an environmental fit problem.
>> Yeah.
>> And this brings us to one of the most staggering statistics in the entire white paper involving Claude code.
>> Yes, the reverse engineering stat. This completely blew my mind.
>> It's incredible. Researchers mapped the entire infrastructure of Claude code version 2.1.88, and they discovered that 98.4%
of the agent's code base was purely operational infrastructure.
>> 98.4%.
>> Yeah. Things like permission classifiers, session storage, retry logic, context compaction pipelines.
Only 1.6% of the code base was the actual prompt reasoning loop.
>> 1.6%.
The AI part of the AI agent is barely a rounding error. That proves your point completely. The foundation model is just a commodity. You can swap the engine out
tomorrow if a cheaper one drops, but the agent skills, the guardrails, the infrastructure, that's the steering wheel and the transmission.
>> Exactly. That is your durable proprietary asset, which is why we have the graduation ladder.
>> Right, the staging area.
>> To your earlier point about a sandbox, skills don't just go live. A new skill starts at the read-only tier where it's evaluated safely by an LLM as a judge.
If it passes, it graduates to draft-only. Here, it can generate outputs and draft emails, but a human has to manually review and approve them
before they go out.
>> And to get to the final tier, action allowed, the paper says it requires a metric called pass to the K. What does that math actually look like?
>> Pass to the K measures sustained reliability.
Let's say a skill succeeds 60% of the time on a single run.
That sounds okay for a quick prototype.
>> Sure.
>> But if you require it to succeed eight times in a row without a critical failure, so pass to the power of eight, that 60% success rate drops to about a
1.6% chance of clearing the hurdle.
>> That is ruthless.
>> It's brutally effective. It exposes inconsistent skills long before they touch production data.
>> That is ruthless, but you know, absolutely necessary. Now, earlier we talked about Path B developers capturing an agent's successful workflow and
turning it into a skill. We are basically letting the AI write its own instructions here.
>> Yeah, we are crossing into the frontier of meta skills.
>> Meta skill.
>> The white paper buckets these into four categories. First is authoring, where tools draft a skill based on a simple human prompt. Second is assisted
authoring from traces, which is Path B.
Third is improvement, where an agent runs bounded automated experiments to optimize an existing skill.
>> Right.
>> And fourth is library evolution, where the agent analyzes, say, a month of chat logs, notices a recurring problem, and
independently proposes a brand new skill to solve it.
>> Okay, I have to step in here. Letting an AI write, update, and evolve its own operating instructions sounds terrifying. What's stopping it from
optimizing for some bizarre metric, over-fitting its own triggers, and quietly destroying our entire library over a weekend?
>> The white paper strongly agrees with your paranoia.
>> Good.
>> Meta skills fall apart completely without that pristine evaluation suite we just discussed.
The absolute non-negotiable rule is that anything an agent writes must enter the library at the draft tier.
>> So, AI can never instantly deploy its own updates.
>> Never. A human must be in the loop for the first few edits. I mean, an agent might optimize a skill's description to pass a specific test, but accidentally
use a trigger phrase that steals traffic from another critical skill.
>> Now,
>> a human reviewer can spot that regression instantly.
>> But wait, keeping humans in the loop for meta skills solves the library destruction problem, but it doesn't solve the traffic jam. If an agent uses
three different skills in a row to complete a complex task, aren't we just dumping all those intermediate outputs back into the context window? Doesn't
that trigger the exact context draw we just tried to escape?
>> Yes. That is the orchestration challenge. You cannot use the context window as a database.
>> Okay, so how do they fix it?
>> Production systems use DAG orchestration.
>> DAG? Woah, directed acyclic graph sounds like a terrifying college math course.
Are we just saying it's a one-way street so the AI doesn't get stuck in an endless loop passing files back and forth?
>> That's exactly what the acyclic part means. No cycles, no infinite loops.
It's a structured map of dependencies.
And to pass the data between these steps without polluting the context window, they use capability profiles over a file message bus.
>> How does a file message bus work in this context?
>> Okay, so instead of the first skill printing a massive 10,000-line JSON output directly into the chat history for the next skill to read,
>> which would blow up the context window.
>> Right. Instead, it saves that JSON to a hidden file on the disk. Then, it just passes the file path URI to the next skill.
>> Oh.
>> The LLM's attention is perfectly protected. It only sees data saved at file X.
The golden rule here is to shift intelligence left.
>> Shift intelligence left. Explain that.
>> It means relying on deterministic software constraints rather than prompt engineering.
Don't write a system prompt yelling in all caps, "Always validate the zip code."
>> Because it's just hoping the LLM will pay attention.
>> Exactly. Shifting intelligence left means you write a rigid five-line Python script in your scripts folder that validates the zip code, and the LLM
simply calls that tool.
>> You rely on code, not vibes. I love that. So, moving from the mechanics to the real world, how is this actually being used in the enterprise right now?
Looking at the ecosystem, there are apparently over 40,000 public skills out there.
Google has their official repository at github.com/ Google skills. How do you even navigate that safely?
>> The paper gives three firm heuristics.
First, prefer first-party skills. If you are querying BigQuery, use the official Google BigQuery skill, not a random community one. Second, pin your versions
aggressively so an unexpected update doesn't break your DAG pipeline. And third, audit the code before adopting.
Remember, a skill can contain executable Python scripts.
>> Oh, right.
>> treat it like a supply chain software dependency.
>> Let's ground all this theory with the case study they included in the appendix B. They looked at a massive home improvement retailer. I really want to
know exactly how a company of that size uses this architecture.
>> They use it to distribute knowledge.
Historically, an AI team at a retailer tries to build one massive monolithic retail assistant. It inevitably fails because AI engineers don't know the
nuances of plumbing codes or lumber grading. With agent skills, the ownership is distributed to the actual domain experts.
>> Let's walk through a specific customer query. Say I go to their site and ask, "I want to tile my shower. What do I need, and can I get it delivered by
Tuesday?" How does that route through the system?
>> The agent dynamically loads three separate skills in sequence. First, it triggers the project guidance skill.
This folder is owned and maintained by the retailer's actual trades team.
>> Okay.
>> It loads the expert logic about waterproofing substrates and grout types. Once the agent figures out the method, it drops that data into the file
message bus.
>> And moves to the next node in the DAG.
>> Exactly. It triggers the materials list skill, which is owned by the pro merchandising team. This skill calculates the exact square footage and wastage.
>> Awesome.
>> Finally, it passes that list to the delivery window skill, owned entirely by the fulfillment team, which runs a deterministic script against the
inventory database to check Tuesday availability.
>> The brilliance of this governance structure is just staggering.
You aren't asking the AI engineering team to become experts in plumbing regulations. The plumbing experts write in a simple markdown file and the AI
just reads it when asked.
>> And that distributed ownership is what creates a company's strategic moat.
>> Right.
>> A competitor can buy access to the exact same base foundation model you are using.
>> But they cannot buy the codified, version controlled institutional knowledge of your best employees.
>> What a journey.
We've gone from unpacking the basic folder structure of a skill.md to understanding how progressive disclosure defeats attention dilution and context
rot. We looked at why trajectory scoring is vital to catch an agent that stumbles into the right answer dangerously.
>> Yeah.
>> And finally, how to use a DAG and a file message bus to deploy a distributed library of institutional knowledge without causing a massive traffic jam.
>> It's a profound shift. We are moving away from trying to make the model inherently smarter and instead focusing on making the environment around the
model highly structured and deterministic.
>> And for everyone listening, don't just let this be an academic theory. We strongly encourage you to actually build this. Jump into the code labs provided
in the 5-day of AI agents, Vibe coding intensive course by Google X Kaggle.
>> Absolutely.
>> Try out the practical implementation of these agent skills yourself. The paper gives incredible advice on where to start tomorrow. Find an expert in your
company, record them doing a manual workflow, draft a skill.md, rate your three JSON evil cases, and ship it to a read-only tier. Just start small.
>> Getting that first successful skill to fire perfectly is a lightbulb moment.
You'll never want to go back to massive system prompts again.
>> It really changes everything. To wrap up our deep dive today, I want to leave you with a thought to mull over, circling
back to that home improvement retailer.
If agent skills effectively digitize and version control the procedural memory, the exact how-to knowledge of your absolute best employees,
what happens to a company's culture and its operations a decade from now when its corporate subconscious consists of hundreds of thousands of skills that
outlive any individual human worker?
>> That is a very big question.
>> Something to think about. Thanks for joining us on this deep dive. We'll see you next time.